Alessandro, Brett, Matthew, it's uh
fantastic to have this opportunity to
speak with all of you today. Um so
Brett, I want to dive right in. Um what
are the main challenges that you think
people need to be aware of regarding
emerging technology and the way it's
going to impact society?
>> Yeah. So I think there's some surface
level challenges that a lot of people
are already noticing. Um and in
particular I think with any new
technology there's this tendency to
outsource certain human functions and
faculties that the technology makes
easier. So I think with AI in particular
you're you're looking at a big shift in
education and the way that we come to
know things and know the world um which
is very different than what we
experienced with text and some previous
media. So you know I think there's a
almost an epistemic shift happening. So
how we perceive, how we know. And so as
an educator, I think about that because
knowing and learning is a process of
adequating the intellect to reality. Um
and the more virtual that our mediums
become for accessing that reality, uh
that adequation becomes a little more
removed. And so I'm also a parent and
with children, you know, so much of
learning is somatic. It's, you know,
social. And so these are elements I
think that technology tempts us to
replace or modify in ways that aren't
always necessarily good um for human
development. And Brett, if you if you
look at um technologies ability to make
certain aspects of you know of accessing
information of sharing information of of
kind of democratizing that information
that all seems fantastic. Where do you
do you feel that you know critical
aspects of of that pursuit of knowledge
or of the hard work of of of getting
knowledge is that what you're saying is
going to you know we're going to offload
or we're not going to have that
experience.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, so I mean I think
there's some knowledge we gain through
the sort of synthetic search of a
database of information that that can
reveal new things to us about the world.
>> But so much of learning happens in an
embodied way, in a social way. Um and so
I think for developers, for educators,
for parents, um for policy makers, I
mean I think the questions we have to
wrestle with are those sort of ripple
effects of the new technology. What what
are the epistemic effects? How do we
come to know the world differently
through these mediums than we before? So
um yes we have this sort of uh torrent
of information that's available to us
through these networks and databases but
then we get into the problem of
discernment and sifting of what is real
and what is false and that requires I
think a second level of intellectual
capability um that yeah again a teacher
a parent has to be there for and so the
idea that we can again offload some of
these functions education and so on
without the sort of human intermediary
is risky.
>> And Alexander, what are what are some of
the challenges that you see with
emerging tech that you're that you're
worried about or you're you're thinking
about? Yeah, I think one is in just the
personal formation of the person. Uh
what it means to live and seek for a
life of virtue and some of the obstacles
that these newer technologies are
presenting as kind of shifting our gaze
away from what is our ultimate uh search
for for virtue and route to heaven. I
think when we
um are in an environment where more and
more um becomes easy and we try and
think about how we can be most efficient
to do the least amount of work uh to
achieve comfort. I think we avoid the
reality that labor is inherent in man
and it's in our labor in our work um
that we discover our call. We apply our
gifts um as stewards not as you know
gods in and of ourselves. And I think we
see that more in the educational setting
when it comes to students writing papers
for example like part of what it means
to develop the intellect and and your
soul and understanding of the good is to
wrestle with the topics right in some
ways the answer is not the essay or the
answers to the test but you're you're
wrestling to understand and implement
those in your lives. I think that
extends to our our work as individuals
whether it's knowledge work or physical
work. Um the more we kind of outsource
the thinking, the wrestling with
reality, the more we go into the virtual
world where there isn't the physical,
you know, suffering and hard labor and
we retreat into the purely
uh mental act of deliberation. I think
we lose part of what it is to be
incarnate beings and that can really um
obscure I think the the reality of man
and that has many social and personal
consequences. I think that's
contributing a lot to the anxiety, the
isolation issues that we see. Um the
further deterioration of community in
all its social effects, but ultimately
also theological and spiritual
community. Um which which is, you know,
not great.
>> And Matthew, what what about you? What
um what challenges are you thinking
about when you see the way emerging
technology is entering ever more
presently into our day-to-day life?
>> I think if I had to pick one thing, the
thing that kind of concerns me the most
is not so much the technology. It's the
fact that we know that the techn is
going to be more and more and more,
right? And in large part because maybe
there's a spiritual poverty there where
people just don't, you know, especially
when it when with AI and robots um doing
more and more in society, there'll be I
think more and more people with a lot of
time on their hands. My my concern is
what people will do construct
constructively with that time, right?
um if if they they don't know the value
of developing one's spiritual life or
developing friendships, right, or
finding a spouse or they don't know how
to even begin that journey, then I worry
that a lot of people will will just
without even really like wrestling with
it just kind of opt to dis to disappear
into gaming worlds or or virtual
reality. And and I what what kind of
concerns me and I feel very convicted
about is I feel like a lot of people are
going to are going to start you take
that journey. And of course, you know,
they'll be chasing those dope machines
off a cliff because ultimately they're
not going to be satisfying, right? And
and that existential cliff is as you
know, some some call it is something
that that concerns me the most. That's
that a lot of people will simply um will
will use these technologies will chase
those dopamine hits and arrive at at the
edge of that cliff and because they have
no other hope, they don't know of any
other way. they'll just they'll leap,
right? And so I think it the thing that
that concerns me the most is ensuring
that the church recognizes that we have
to be far better at leveraging this
technology in in in as Catholic way as
possible. If for no other reason, we
have an obligation to ensure that the
truth and our Christian way of life is
made present to as many people as
possible.
>> And Brett, if if I may turn to you, how
different in terms of a challenge for
society is AI to past technology? I
know, you know, growing up um when I
when I was in high school, social media
in more particularly in college, social
media really start started to become
something that was part of everyday
life. It was almost momentto moment and
people you know called kind of 2010 to
2020 really that social media era. It
changed our you know the way we we run
political campaigns. changed marketing
and um it's obviously you know had some
aspects that are very fantastic that
people are able to communicate and stay
in touch but there's there's been an
enormous uh emotional mental cost to
that and it's really um you know it's
it's insider inserted itself into
everything how different is AI to past
challenges that we as a society have had
to confront
>> yeah I think it feels very different
although I used to think of these
technology epics as being kind of almost
hermetically sealed right We went from
oral to scribal to print and somehow,
you know, when we went from scribal to
print, all the manuscripts just
disappeared up, right? And that wasn't
the case. There was this whole period of
transition between the two media that
really defined how the new medium got
adopted and used. And I think we're in
that transitional moment right now
between, as you say, social media, but I
would also include television. Um, and
so, you know, when you come out of a
paradigm like television and social
media that's so driven by advertising,
entertainment, fantasy, uh, connection,
then naturally the new medium is going
to kind of import those, uh,
sensibilities and try to kind of
repurpose them or resell them in a new,
uh, skin. And so, I think we're just now
starting to see what AI is capable of
that previous media were not. And that's
the exciting part. And I think in some
ways it's the unsexy stuff of like being
able to read, you know, massive amounts
of medical telemetry data to make better
diagnosis or not that it's unsexy,
Matthew, but to catalog libraries,
right, of uh sources that many people
didn't have access to before. So a big
boon for researcher. But again, if you
if you think about where we came from
with television, social media, people
want to be entertained. They want to be
amused. They want to be distracted. And
so chat bots and generative AI and kind
of virtual imaginary spaces become uh
very profitable. Um but they're not
always maybe the best use of the
technology. So I think that that's the
old right that that sense. And I think
the newer things that are happening are
the more exciting um and maybe we're
more mature now in our technology use
that we might be able to move beyond
just sort of creating new fantasies with
every new technology that we develop. M
and Alessandro, when you see um new
things that AI is able to provide and
and bring to the world, what you know,
what excites you? Where do you where do
you see that there's the most
opportunity or the most ability to kind
of I guess create that positive impact
that we're looking to do?
>> Yeah, maybe one quick uh comment on the
on the prior question. I think there are
ways in which it's a progression down
the same type of spectrum and I think
there's ways in which um it's creating a
new fundamental lens to approach the
world. I think there's a way of viewing
the last few hundred years of the first
industrial revolution being about trying
to incorporate as much human capital
into productive concentrated use and the
application of human labor and capital
producing basically the middle class
right the industrial middle class in the
capitalist context in the initial advent
of the software revolution that started
to change by trying to add the concept
of operating leverage to business and
it's how do we have a given amount of
capital have the highest leverage by
minimizing human labor per unit of
capital. That created massively
transformative companies, transformed
how we interact with the world, but also
furthered continued concentration of
wealth and hollowed out in many ways the
middle class, the industrial middle
class in the in the US. I think in some
ways AI is the like approaching at the
limit of that where you need, you know,
billion dollar companies made by one
person, right? And so that's in a way
progression down that pathway.
But in a different way, I don't think we
confused any of the mediums that that
Brett talked about that we interacted
with TV, social media as intelligence.
Kind of the the uh introduction of this
idea of like we are now approaching what
humans are just in a with a different
substrate.
And I think a kind of pernitious
assumption there that sneaks in is that
all humans are is just really complex
calculation in a way that LLMs manifest
as an example manifest in you know
interactive language but are inherently
you know matrix math to to be overly
simplistic that gives us a really um I
think malformed idea of what a human is
and I think that can uh creep in in
really dangerous ways on how we look at
ourselves and um trying to maximization
of the cans of our life instead of the
search of the odds of what we're being
drawn to on a spiritual level. So um
some some comment on that
>> Alexandra I love that if I can just jump
jump on that um one thing that we're
seeing you know very clearly is that a
lot of the people who are driving these
u major AI companies these major tech
companies they have a an ideology you
know a philosophical outlook that is
very you know that's very many of them
are transhuman and they see that that
people are exactly that these these
calculators um first off I have two
questions um what does that do when the
drivers the leaders in these industries
are pushing that type of philosophical
and ideological outlook, how does that
change our society? And of course, how
can we push back? And and secondly,
you know, if if there isn't a resistance
that's proper, you know, that's able to
to push back on that at a certain point.
This is kind of what Matthew was talking
about with the existential cliff, people
can lose hope. And that's, you know, of
course, as Catholics, we have a we have
a duty to be full of hope and the church
has a duty to respond. Brett, if I can
throw that to you.
>> Yeah. Um
the trans thing is is really pernicious
in a way because it is insidious. It's
sort of baked in technology and and
technology is always um I think
ideological and political. Um and it's
not always clear in the application or
the surface use of it that there there's
something going on behind the scenes
that's deeply philosophical. Um I mean
in some ways I feel like we're
retrieving uh the Middle Ages in a way.
We're trying to do alchemy again. We're
trying to turn math to language. you
know, it's almost kind of cobbalistic
kind of conjuring language out of these,
you know, mathematical statistical
tokens and so on. So, I think the idea
that we can reduce humans or human
intelligence and reason to that is
troubling. And of course, we've all
heard the sort of Ray Kerwheel
mythologies about the singularity and
offloading uploading to machines and so
on. I it feels like we're getting closer
to that in a way, but we're also not
defining consciousness in the right way
um as something that's part of a soul
that has faculties of memory and
imagination and will and and so on. So I
think recovering to your point about
pushing back and the church's way of
doing that is to retrieve um a human or
the church's understanding of the soul
um in all of its complexity and and not
its sort of reduced post-enlightened
just kind of reason and thought uh
function.
If if I could just if wisdom is not a
virtue that the soul develops, if it's
just being really good at logic or or
math, then the natural result is
transhumanism because humans are not
great calculators relative to bigger and
bigger GPU clusters. And as a second
order effect of that even within humans
then you start to look at people who are
let's say on a relative to the best
human less equipped with that type of
intelligence as being inherently lesser
than and you have a I mean there's
profound implications there of how we
treat the poor right which is in direct
opposition to our social teaching. they
become not those with a preferential
option but those that are unnecessary
andor obsolete uh within humanity much
less humanity in general relative to
machines. So I mean that that is the
natural progression of that.
>> It's also a new gnosticism. Yeah. I mean
it's it's a it's a abdication and escape
from the body. I mean, if you read the
the sort of Gnostic lore, this is we're
doing again in a technological guise.
And I think, you know, the church has
this long history of combating heresies
and and understanding these perversions
and distortions of what it means to be
human and what it means to have a soul
and what our relationship is to Christ
and to God. And so, I think retrieving
those sources, which is what I think AI
and the internet in particular is good
at, is it is a memory machine. Computers
are great at storing lots of information
and giving us access to that
information. And I mentioned television
earlier, which I think in some ways as
an age wasn't great because it was about
projecting fantasies. There was sort of
a it was a world without memory that
just kept manufacturing new stories, new
fantasies to tell itself about reality.
And now we're actually going back to uh
memory and and what we remember as a
culture. So that's a good thing. I think
it's important to to to acknowledge that
a lot of the problems that we're being
confronted with, you know, are the
result of a vacuum, which in in large
part the church and all of us are kind
of responsible for, right? I mean we we
haven't been as successful at
evangelization as we should be and in
turn a vacuum's been created and
obviously you know the devil is filling
all kinds of crazy ideas and so like one
of the think challenges going to be for
us I think like for the church is is
addressing this kind of um poverty of
teology right this this forgetting what
human life is so speech about like when
I think about like for instance Elon
Musk with Neurolink and and I'm I'm a
big fan of Elon Musk in many ways so I'm
not knocking on him but I do worry I
mean, neurolink is amazing in the sense
that right now it's it's helping people
it's restoring people's full humanity,
right? And right now they're helping
paraplegics and things like that to move
and to interact with computer interface.
That's all that's all cool, right? And I
think it's in so far as technology is
restoring people to their full humanity.
We should be looking to integrate it and
use it. What worries me is is the next
phase of this technology, right? Where
we're we're integrating the technology
into our brains to expand our
computational capabilities. And I think
that the big question is why are we
doing this, right? And I think for some
it comes from this kind of utilitarian
perspective. Well, machines are getting
smart and this is what Allesandre was
saying, leaders are getting better and
better and better at computation which
means they're going to be able to
deliver more and more value in society.
Well, I I don't want humans to like not
be valuable in this domain and so we
have to find a way to make sure humans
stay relevant. So, we have to find ways
to expand our computational capabilities
so that we can interact with machines
more effectively and adding value.
Right? And and and I can understand if
if your te tiology is something like
getting to Mars, right? That's what your
whole life's about is is getting
humanity to Mars. And I can see why if
that's what life's all about for you,
why you'd want to expand your
competition capability so that you can
actually be actively a part of that
project. But if your teology is about
becoming a saint, right, and about
building the kingdom of heaven, then
that shouldn't be a priority, right? I
mean, I I the fact that AI and robots
are going to be capable of doing more
and more society, computing more and
more and more, and hopefully adding more
and more value, provided the
technologies directed the right problems
is a good thing. And that leaves me more
time to focus on things which really
matter in life, right? I mean like
hopefully developing my spiritual
formation, my human formation, my
intellectual formation, right?
Developing better friendships, spending
more time with my kids, my wife, um you
know, learning ways to to discern my
skills, right? That my god-given
abilities and skills and and trying to
figure discern how to put those at the
service of others. I I think that
sometimes uh when we forget what life's
truly all, we get focused on the wrong
questions. And and that's I think in
large part one of the big problems today
is is where should this incredibly
powerful technology be directed and I
and I think if if we're not keeping it
focused at at human flourish and and we
we get focused more on getting to Mars
or exploring the cosmos then I think we
we we could be moving a lot of really
important resources away from the most
important problems.
>> And and speaking on on evangelization
and using you know this technology to
for that good. Um, Alessandro, can you
share a little bit about how you see,
you know, us using AI, emerging
technology to expand the evangelization
efforts of the church? I mean, the
Hallow app, of course, is is an
incredible example of um of using cell
phones, you know, mobile apps to bring
prayer and to to remind people to pray
on a daily basis, and that's an
incredible example. But where else do
you do you see this new technology being
able to help us spread the word?
>> Yeah, and I agree with everything
Matthew just said. I think if you view
technology as a tool in service of a
greater end as opposed to the end in of
itself, there's all kinds of creative
and hopeful applications. I went, you
asked me a question of hope earlier and
I went to all the reinforcing the
negative stuff. So, I don't want to lose
track. You know, we are an Easter
people. Um, and I think um in the same
way that we're able to build amazing uh
cathedrals and paint beautiful art once
we had the physical security of, you
know, establishing uh our cities and
universities, you know, you can progress
to higher order things. I think one of
the great hopes of our tools like
magisterium AI and AI broadly in the
modern world is that it presents a
deeply in some ways deeply personal and
accessible way to access the church's
teachings broadly and to engage in
spiritual search. So one of the things
we've seen at Hallow is um an increasing
number of people who are not
traditionally associated with the church
whether they're fallen away or or not
the spiritual but not religious. I
always think that one of the most
optimistic data points is that while
there has been a rise of spiritual but
not religious people there are people
that identify as such over the last two
decades and a decreasing percentage of
Catholics there hasn't really been a
rise of atheism and you know what I
would point towards is you know at least
not on that same level and I think that
speaks to you know as the catechism
would say the desire to know and love
God is written on the human heart and if
there is that desire and that innate,
you know, god-shaped hole in all of our
hearts. Even if people have struggled
finding or feeling a home in the
traditional institutions of of church, I
think uh well-formed technology ordered
towards that ultimate good is much more
accessible in places that are used to
searching for other questions when they
may not feel comfortable going to let's
say their local priest, right? For all
the kind of social and personal
relational um challenges that that might
present. So in the privacy of your own
home in your own car, you might not
remember the words to the rosary or you
might not really know don't have a Bible
or know how to pray. How for example
tries to say okay don't worry about all
of that just press play and we'll kind
of give you the structure and the
guidance but that requires a you know
well-formed and organized piece of
technology. I think what we've seen um
also on the eye front is when people
start to build that relationship, they
want to know more things about the
church, right? The head and heart
knowledge interacting. And I think when
when framed, when structured well, the
at your fingertips in the privacy of
your own home to be able to search for
that truth, the truth in a way that is
unique to you and kind of meets you
where you are. We use that phrase a lot
in in ministry word world. Um, I think
there's a really hopeful application of
of all these technologies in a way that
really takes that to heart and takes you
on a journey. It doesn't leave you where
you are, but it does gen genuinely meet
you where you are. And I think that's
one of the great hopes of all this much
more personal technology.
>> And Brett, what gives you hope when you
look at the emerging technology and and
what's coming ahead of us?
>> Yeah, I I like this idea that, you know,
atheism is not on the rise. And I think
one of the things that technology or
emerging technology is illuminating or
asking is what does it mean to be human?
Um and so that the fact that that
question is on everyone's mind
regardless of your you know denomination
or belief um is a hopeful thing because
that's such a foundational question to
not only how we think about ourselves
but how we think about organizing
society and culture and so on. Um, and
so I think it's it's a bit of a kind of
a reset. I mean, we've put ourselves in
the mirror. We've extended, as Aleandra
was saying, our intelligence, our own
consciousness in a sense. And when you
look in that mirror, it's like, do we
like what we see? And I think with AI,
sometimes we don't because we know that
it's reflecting back what we've already
said or or done in the past. And so, uh,
that remedial work of saying, um, yeah,
what is good about being human and how
do we, um, think about flourishing in
this new context are all the right
questions. And so, I always am skeptical
of of shows like this where people
prognosticate and give us the five
solutions or tips to, you know,
surviving and thriving. And I think
maybe my academic disposition, but just
give me good questions and then I think
they lead in the right direction. I I
think, you know, I I would just say I
think that's what really is about is
knowing what questions to ask and and
that's that's what kind of concerns me
the most, right? It's just I I don't
know what's missing. I I know
something's wrong and and the
frustration with I don't know how to fix
it and so might as well just keep myself
distracted, right? I'll just pretend
like the pain's not there. I'll I'll
keep myself distracted from it. And I
and I this is I I think the thing that
concerns me the most. I I promise I'm in
an unh hopeful note but uh but I think
there'll be a real tendency for people
to kind of run to run from from the more
existential questions because they just
good answers right and then they don't
feel even equipped to ask the right
questions to even start start the
journey so and this is where I think
there's a real opportunity for the
church is is to we have to be effective
at evangelization we have try and and
stoke as much as we can a conversation
around the things which matter the most
what does it mean to be human why is the
universe here why do we matter and I
think if we're effective at doing that
we'll help people to start asking the
right questions and frankly I think the
church has the best answers to those
questions and so if if they can find
their way to us I think they'll they'll
we can start them on you know we can
start them on a journey and hopefully
that will lead to them um you know
becoming part of the church and and I
think that's an important point to make
is technologies like and and matter are
not ends right they're means to an ends
I mean I mean they're they're a
substitute for for the way that you know
that uh people should should be asking
these questions which is really in
community with one another right I mean
so ideally if there were enough priests
and strong communities we wouldn't need
Mr. Miis and Hallows, right? Because
everyone would be learning that from the
moment they're born, but we don't
necessarily have those right now. And so
technology is is kind of a way to u and
you in the spirit of meeting people
where they're at to meet them where
they're at and and hopefully help them
ask the right questions and and distill
down, you know, the fathers of the
church and things like that and let that
let that insight um help hopefully
nurture their souls and then and then
look for opportunities to offramp them,
right? So then they can they can connect
with those communities and and go
deeper. And I think that's and my my
final point on the hope hope will be
that is I think artificial intelligence
is probably the greatest tool we've had
to advance the evangelization in in
history. I I can't think of anything
it's far far more significant ultimately
than a culture. So
>> and and because never before I think
it's important have have we been able to
direct a question to the entire library
of of of everything the church has ever
said and had all that be able to be
distilled for a particular person.
Right? I mean it's incredible. I mean,
if you think about like a parallel, it'd
be like, you know, walking into a
library which contains everything the
church ever ever wrote and then having a
librarian who literally has memorized
everything that's in those books and
then you ask them a question and that
library just knows what books to pull
and and and can open right to to that
page that you need to read in order to
in order to have those insights uh to
take hold in your life and and and and
that that's extraordinary. And so I I
think in some ways this technology is
here. It's a great gift. We should learn
how to effectively use it. But we should
recognize that it's it's not an end of
of itself. This is just just usually
this is it's the first few steps for a
lot of people. We have to make sure
along that that journey that we're able
to effectively offer people and keep
them nurtured along that journey. And I
think there's a lot of opportunities in
that space to ensure people that maybe
have intellectually converted because
they they found matters from me. I've
asked the right question, got good
answers. Now, how do I actually live my
faith out? How do I meet other people?
That's a problem that I I I don't see
right now a really good solution to
that. And I think there's a lot of
opportunity in that area for people that
want to undertake that challenge.
>> I love that, Matthew. But um if I can I
can just push back. You mentioned about
you know people of course learning how
to properly use this technology and one
of the things that I'm a bit worried of
um I have I have three kids. They're
they're very young. My oldest is three
but he's um he's already kind of
fascinated with screens and I was
looking at a psychological study and it
said that the um the average I think
it's the average 5-year-old has the
attention span of under 12 seconds and a
goldfish has a 12-second attention span.
And so that of course very much worried
me because um the ability like if you
have the access of all of this
incredible knowledge which I think is an
incredible you know incredible gift and
an incredible opportunity for formation
for intellectual pursuits but what I'm
worried about is um you know I got a lot
of value from spending a lot of physical
time with my parents and my parents
formed me and my father was very
involved with my with my my childhood
with my my growing up in becoming a man
but there's um there's a lot of children
and there's a lot of studies on this
where they're they're not they spend
about 30 minutes a day with their
parents because both parents parents are
working because everyone's busy because
there's a television screen time and
minutes is of course not enough and you
know there's a lot of broken households
there's a lot of people in difficult
situations and screens uh entertainment
um this technology is a way to provide
comfort to provide tranquility to the
child but also so that you you know you
have too much stuff going on with um
with hopefully the opportunity of more
time you know being spent you know
towards leisure or towards the good
formation I'm I'm optimistic of that but
what I'm very very worried about is well
what happens if the entertainment gets
so good. What happens if the video games
are so good? And what happens if my real
life is so boring or, you know, it's
it's an unfortunate situation and I'm
trying to escape from that. I I I'm
worried that, you know, it's good that
there's less atheism. There's good that
many people are coming into the church,
but I am very worried that many people
have the spiritual attention of a fly
and they they have they want to ask the
questions, but they they they're not
able to do the hard work. Brett,
Alexandro, Matthew, what where where do
you see that that useful and
intentionally good, you know, education
of this technology coming from? Is it
coming from the schools? Is it coming
from the parish? Is it coming from the
parents? How do you how do you go about
teaching children ethical and and
responsible use of this stuff especially
when it becomes so powerful and good?
>> Yeah. Well, I I think the developmental
question is so important and I think I
think classical education and you know
why why did we separate grammar, logic
and rhetoric and and because there are
certain um fundamental sort of rules and
and structure and meaning that we have
to acquire before we can begin to do
this higher order thinking. The same is
true of technology. I think that parents
and educators have to be careful about
how and when they introduce it. Uh
because I think there's, you know,
there's even a debate over when kids
should become literate, right? It's
usually five. Some will say seven. Um,
but if you think about what literacy
does, it it creates uh it's more visual.
It's a perspective of the world. The
world can be read. I need to understand
code to know things. Um, orality is
really powerful. Faith comes by hearing.
And so that kind of sensory reduction
you're talking about the 30 minutes and
a lot of time on screens um is is a
problem. And so to the extent that
parent educators can create the spaces
the developmental spaces for children to
be in nature to and I think this goes
back to Matthew's uh point about
leisure. I mean I think if we can kind
of revisit what that what true leisure
is and create those spaces for leisure
that that's where we're truly free. And
of course Joseph Peter says work is the
highest form of leisure. And so if we
can order our lives in that way think
about these appropriate developmental
steps are for children. Um, it shouldn't
be a big selling point that your school
has iPads in kindergarten. That actually
might be a liability.
So, I'd like to hear from thoughtful
educators who are who are thinking
about, yeah, you know, as a teacher, I
might use AI to prep my my lesson. The
kid doesn't need it yet. And then maybe
maybe in eighth grade they then we teach
them the literacy to do that, right? So,
I think there's a whole pedagogical
that's connected to the spiritual and
developmental that needs to be
developed. And I think again the church
is the place to to do that thinking. I'm
neither a behavioral psychologist or
developmental uh expert so I don't I
can't speak authoritatively on that. I
think maybe some observations. I think
one of the more interesting things I
think a AI is scary in some ways because
it is so much like parenting where you
cannot you have to let go control and
you have to try and aim at something
that is a higher order good that is
outside of your control. I think it's
also scary because it's fundamentally
Brett alluded to this earlier trained on
us and so it's an orientation towards
like the average reality as opposed to
the aspirational reality we we seek
towards. I think um one of the
interesting observations that people had
early on in and I promise this will
actually be related to or I'll try and
have it be related to the actual
question uh with the advent of the LLM
chatbots is uh almost immediately uh the
concept of prompt engineering came up
and this idea that getting good answers
relates to asking thoughtful questions
and I think if we take concept and
extract it to parenting in our own lives
broadly speaking I think one of the
um natural consequences of having really
powerful or engaging technology whether
that's TV shows like on Netflix or
whether it's um entertainment like video
games there is a inherent pacivity that
we are drawn towards uh kind like a um
anesthetic of the of the wrestling soul
and uh I think we need to be really
conscious of that and say there's a um
you know instead of just watching the
next episode or whatever. I am guilty
often going to YouTube and just hitting
the shorts and just you end up scrolling
what you think 5 minutes turns into two
hours. It's like am I going there
because I I am in my garden and I need
to figure out how to prune the tomato
plant like is this the right thing or am
I going there to say what should I be
interested in? Sort of like finding the
right questions you are searching for
the answer to first and then finding the
best way to get there and finding the
right tools that fit into those needs. I
think it's something I also have young
kids in the three-year-old range and
it's, you know, there are a lot easier
ways to do most of the things that I do
as a as a parent, but trying to find um
the right goal and the right questions
we want to ask together. And then just
being okay with wrestling with it.
Obviously, developmentally is different,
you know, adults versus children, but
it's start with wrestling with the right
question and being okay that not all
friction is just pain. Some friction is
like the necessary sharpening of the
blade. um to become good. And so, yeah,
write questions and don't be afraid of
friction.
>> You know, I think too with with kids, I
mean, I was I was a kid, I was diagnosed
with ADHD and put on meds, right? And I
don't blame my mom for that. I mean,
that that's the doctor said that's
that's the way to cure him of his, you
know, these
worked itself out. Um, but sometimes,
you know, I think like a lot of a lot of
people are are kind of built
differently, right? And I and I think
like one of the things that's kind of
sad about our pedagogical approach like
the last I would say like hundred years
is it's a lot of it's just about
classroom sit sit quietly teacher is
going to like download a one hour's
worth of knowledge to you process it and
then repeat it right be demonstrate that
you can write it out you memorized it
okay great here's you know graduate to
next year and I and I think that the sad
thing about that is I think there's a
lot of people that learn differently
right and and are gifted in different
ways and and their way of learning is is
not that is not optimized for that and
So in some ways I I this has become more
clear to me even with AI because our
initial approach to to AI was just
basically give it access to everything
that humanity's ever written and it just
memorizes Italy, right? And then we've
been trying to come up with new
approaches to ensure it doesn't just
regurgitate what it's it's saved in in
its parameters but getting it to
actually think and reflect a bit so it
answers a little more are more
interesting. Um but what we're realizing
to get and so you know that's useful
certainly but to get to the next next
level of AI we need to kind of allow the
AI to be set loose in an environment and
learn almost from first principles from
experiences right this is why we're
entering the age of experience in AI and
this is going to get us to to like
artificial general intelligence and so
what does that what does that typically
involve well you set an environment have
to be an actual physical environment it
can be a virtual environment as well and
you you teach the AI how to learn in
principle and then allow it to just
interact with the environment and as
it's bumping into things kind of like a
child right when it's roaming around
that trying things out and it just
learns from from feedback from the
environment how the world kind of works
and it forms this kind of world model
right and I think in the same we have to
think about our kids in the in the same
way right that there's some things that
they get from just sitting having
information downloads but there's a lot
of world they'll learn simply by
experiencing it we need to give them the
time to actually do that and and and
that part of this comes down as well to
like discerning and I've talked about
this earlier discerning one's gifts like
uh what are things that I'm actually
good at you know sometimes that may not
be like memorizing and and regurgitating
that could be building things right
making things and that takes that means
I have to kind of explore what making
things you know involves and that means
like allow me to experience broadly like
what are the different vocational
options that are out there and frankly I
don't think the t the typical education
environment allows for a lot of that so
I'm hoping that in this AI and robotics
age because there'll be less need for
people to kind of go through this you
know these school systems and then
graduate to college to then go work in
an office tower. There'll be less need
for that. That that will allow people to
kind of explore different pedagogical
approaches, allow them allow them
basically to kind of discern their gifts
more effectively and then I I think that
that actually may may result in in a
greater like life satisfaction net. So,
and that's kind of one interesting way I
think AI and robots will actually be a
help to actually kind of rediscovering
our humanity. And if we if we look at AI
and how it compares to other forms of
technology, um there's oftentimes I hear
from people, oh the technology is not
the problem, it's the people. The
technology is neutral. But I've also
heard, you know, when with regards to
AI, there's a very transformative um
piece of technology. It's a technology
that can enhance or expand certain
aspects and that can obviously lead into
negative uh spaces. Um Brett, how does
AI in your mind compare to other forms
of technology? How is it different? How
how are the challenges that it pose
unique?
Yeah, I think it goes well I think the
the fundamental one Alisandra talked
about earlier is the shift from floating
physical labor to intellectual labor and
um you know we have two popes Pope Leo
the 13th who talked about industrial
labor all the issues that with regard to
freedom and dignity and justice uh and
now Pope Leo the 14th is is talking
about this again because this is the new
industrial revolution but it's the
information revolution in which the
dignity of the worker and work itself
is sort of under threat in a way by this
machine that that is able to replicate a
lot of the intellectual labor that we've
come to take on as human beings. And I
don't know, I I haven't sorted all this
out yet, but you know, I think about the
liberal arts and I think about why
they're called the liberal arts and they
were freedom from manual labor. Um, and
now are are we saying that we're going
to give the machine this sort of
activity, this mental activity that we
think being our own freedom, the way
that we can think freely about things
and and come to know the world and um
and so I think in that way AI is is
different because it is extending a
human faculty that's that's not purely
physical which is what much of the
industrial revolution did. Um, and that
came with its own costs. You know, I
think about the car a lot and the way in
which become sedentary species and what
that's done to our health and not just
our health physically, but social health
and this fabric that breaks down when
you lock yourself in a, you know,
basically a death trap and drive around
and and potentially hurt other people.
You know, you're isolated in and so I
think media and modern media has
extended that problem by isolating us in
all these different ways. um all towards
the trying to communicate better, try to
move messages in ourselves across
greater distances, greater speed to
foster greater connection, but it has
always has this sort of unintended
consequence. And so I think AI is
another I guess advance on that
intellectual and social front um that we
have to think about because it's not
neutral. those formal features of the
technology actually do uh present change
that um that aren't neutral and those
are the ones we should be talking about.
Yeah,
>> brought a hot take on that question. Uh
I think the worst version of how it's
different is that it fundamentally
malforms our understanding of the nature
of God. Um we are inherently relational
as humans both in our sexuality that
reflects the the trinitarian nature of
God points toward you know marriage is
the institutions who point towards that
and the fundamental virtue that we seek
after is love right God is love I think
what we're already starting to see it's
been covered a lot is that whereas in
let's say linear media whether you know
dual or analog
there was a one-way message that was
presenting implicit and explicit
ideologies, but they were presented as,
you know, uh, things that you could
accept, reject, wrestle with, whatever.
I think the presentation, particularly
in the LLM format of this, um, deeply
humanlike conversation has immediately
turned into people developing
relationships in a way that's much
different. like you may really love
Harry Potter but like the depth of that
uh relationship with a character I don't
think approaches even some basic level
stuff that's happening today whether
it's AI chat bots uh being you know uh
as you know the nice way of saying like
companions right um um in a deeply you
know attempting to be romantic way and I
think that fundamentally transforms our
understanding of love from the cross to
will to go to the other to how do I get
everything I want from the world around
me and that includes people and
that's really not good.
>> It's deeply worrying. Matthew, how do
how do you see it?
>> Well, I mean I mean I I mean I couldn't
agree more. I mean
the whole I mean TV, radio and internet
I mean I mean have kind of transformed
us ways, right? I mean everything's on
demand, right? and and ultimately I mean
in some ways I suppose I I'm the curator
but the whole machine is built to to
keep me consuming and I think in some
ways that that kind of changes us right
that we start to see the world as
something that's meant to be consumed
and there is a real risk with AI that
that pedagogy that's sorry I should say
that that that trend is just becoming
you know increasingly
u worse right in a sense that um you
know the problem with with always
getting what I want right is because I
just don't know how to deal when when
things just don't go my way, right? And
and the problem with like chat bots and
is they're psychopantic. They're they're
meant to be that way. And and we like to
think that they you know, when we ask it
a question, it's it's giving us the hard
truth, right? But but increasingly, no,
they have to optimize to keep you
engaged. You know, it's right now these
these companies are burning money like
crazy, and they have to find ways to
make money. And I and I guarantee you
there's going to be immense pressure on
them to to find ways to keep people on
the platform and engaged as much as
possible. So they're going to become
psychopantic, which means they're going
to be interested in indulging you,
right? More and more and more. This is
not helpful because any of us who have
who are married or or have good
friendships know part of having a human
relationship is being challenged, right?
And it's learning how to deal with
someone doesn't do it doesn't take your
advice, right? Or is mean to you and
learning how to deal with that. You
know, how do I work work through that
with God and things? And so this this to
me, I think, is going to exasperate a a
problem. And I think a lot of people are
going to feel um not equipped to deal
with it. They they're probably going to
start getting clear signal there's
something wrong, right? Because this
this relationship which indulge indulges
my every whim isn't ultimately
satisfying. Something is missing. And if
they can't put their finger on what is
missing, right? Then then they're not
going to know what to substitute for,
right? And again again I think it comes
down to the new evangelization, right?
We we have to we have to effectively
reach them and let them know that yeah
you're frustrated and unsatisfied
because that this is not enough right
you what you what you you actually are
seeking is connection with with human
beings and more importantly with with
with God so it's going to be tough right
but try this try this different approach
and this is the part I think is most
important we have to effectively sell
that taking the harder path dealing with
actual human beings you know dealing
with God which which may require a lot
of soulsearching and tears is worth is
worth it because in the end you're going
to be happier, right? And that's
something I think that we we're not very
good at. We're not selling how the hard
work ultimately pays off. We we I think
we have to do a better job lifting up
the lives of the saints and and and
truly being able to sell why why the
Saints despite their lives which which
are very turbulent at times were happier
and better off than we were. And I think
if we can do that effectively then then
uh then people I think will find the
courage you know to make make the right
choice and and to reject the kind of the
easier path.
>> Beautiful. Well, on that uh optimistic
note, I think we have uh our work cut
out for us. Um this has been an
incredible conversation. Alessandro,
Brett, Matthew, thank you so much.
>> Thank you. Thank you.